today we're going to begin our overview
of the history of philosophy with an
introduction to the Modern Age we did a
transition in the last session and now
we move to the 17th century
and the 17th century is typically called
The Age of Reason
because the school of thought called
rationalism was the dominant school of
thought during this period now not that
there weren't the tractors and people
who came at it from different views but
the dominant overwhelming movement in
philosophy in the 17th century was in
the school of rationalism
now probably the most important figure
for us to look at who is representative
of this Modern Age
is Renee Descartes
Descartes dates are 1596.
2 16 50.
he was educated
by Jesuits
and was a loyal son of the Roman
Catholic Church
but his principal field of
specialization was the science of
mathematics and that's a curiosity that
we have to see here because
in the Age of Reason or the age of
rationalism many of the most significant
thinkers of that day were not only
philosophers but they were mathematics
that should or mathematicians that
should strike a Accord in your memory
bank here remembering back to Plato
who saw such a close relationship
between philosophical thought and
mathematical Concepts in his theory of
forms and I mentioned in passing
that in one sense mathematics is a form
of symbolic logic
now before we get the Descartes himself
I want to mention one other thing about
mathematics
at this time of worldwide Revolution
particularly with the new discoveries in
science and astronomy and so on so much
of the Innovative work in the world of
science
at that time
came about through the result of the
theories postulated by mathematicians
it was it was the mathematicians who
figured out the new astronomy
and it was Newton you know who came up
with the new physics and that's been
characteristically the way it happens in
physics and in science when we think of
our own day of the radical changes in
Life as we know it because of the work
of Albert Einstein who was a
mathematician but his work led us into
the atomic age now in very simple terms
the way that works is this somebody
works out some mathematical equations
with a pad and a paper with a pencil
and then applies those equations to real
concrete experiences in the world
and they begin to project
the findings from the mathematical
equations into reality
for example somebody did a study of of
the moons of Jupiter and saw that that
mathematically there should have been
one more at a certain place well they
point the telescope there and voila
there it is and what arose during this
period was an unbridled sense of
optimism with respect to the ability of
the science of mathematics to continue
to be the avant-garde of all scientific
discovery because it had performed in
such an astonishing way up to that point
now we'll see a little bit more about
what that means when we look now at the
thinking of Descartes Descartes
began his work during this period of
radical upheaval
where the monolithic authority of the
church had collapsed
the old medieval systems of the guilds
had collapsed
the political structures of Europe had
changed and it was a very unsettling
period for many folks because in the
most part while the church was
dominating things and had the monolithic
Authority that it enjoyed
people were content to get their
questions answered by the dictates of
the church and so that the idea
that the church had espoused
the fides implicitum
were the implicit faith that people were
to give to the truth of God had been
transferred to the truths
declared by the church and by Church
Tradition now all of a sudden there's a
crisis because the Protestant
Reformation had brought about the
greatest disintegration of unity of the
Christian institutional Church in her
history
and so the simple problem that people
faced was that authorities
that heretofore were United
and agreed with each other were now in
very serious and profound conflict
and so the person on the street was
asking who can I trust who do I believe
are the Roman Catholics right or are the
lutherans right or the Presbyterians the
Calvinists or whoever
and people now were exposed to both
positions and there was a great
unsettling of the human spirit with
respect to the whole question of Truth
now some people responded to this with a
new kind of skepticism and simply
despaired of ever discovering truth but
that wasn't the personality of Descartes
Descartes stepped into this situation of
confusion and skepticism and he said I
want to find certainty
I want to have a knowledge of truth that
I can rely on
without being open to the vagaries of
public opinion
and being a student of mathematics he
was trying to find truths that were as
certain to him as the
conclusions that could be reached doing
the work of math
and so he wrote a book
which was very important
called the discourse on method
he's also famous for his other work the
meditations but the discourse on method
was the book in which he introduced his
method or his way of thinking in order
to arrive at certainty and in truth
he said that that the method of
searching for truth involves two
elements
intuition
and deduction now I have to pause here
because when we talk about the term
intuition
we liken it to some kind of an
imaginative sense or a hunch or
the thing my wife expresses when we
disagree and I try to give a reason for
my position and she says what good is
that I have an intuition and it's over
but the uh the idea that he's using the
way in which he's using the I the word
intuition
is to describe a rational concept a
rational idea
that is so clear
and so distinct
that it is manifestly undeniable
so what he was looking for what he was
caught what he was calling clear and
distinct ideas
so that once you have those axioms or
those basic primary truths that to doubt
them is to affirm them
they are Givens as it were of reality
those clear and distinct ideas form one
part of his method the second part of
his method is the application of the
principles of deduction
now
when we talk about deduction we talk
about deducing
conclusions from premises which
conclusions follow
necessarily from the premises when we
talked about Aristotle's delineation of
the science of logic you recall he saw
that the first element of logic was the
law of non-contradiction but in addition
to that there were also the laws of
immediate inference
the laws of immediate inference
and these laws govern
the relationship of certain inferences
that are drawn from premises or from
propositions
for example
if it's true
then all men are mortal
what would that say which happens to be
a general affirmative proposition a
universal affirmative
what would that say about the statement
some men are mortal
would that statement be true Roger if
all men are mortal would it also be true
that some people or men are mortal I
suppose
it wouldn't be true
well let me put it this way if all cats
were Gray
would some cats be Gray
yes sir so that here we have a
particular affirmation that would be
obviously true right if all men are
mortal then it'd certainly be true that
some men are mortal you may say well
wait it's not true because you're not
saying enough because it's more than
some it's all no but if all are
something then certainly some are
now suppose I said all men are mortal
and some men are not mortal
true or false
false because if all are in this
particular category then you can't have
some who aren't in that category and so
the laws of immediate inference
are drawn to show instantly on the
computer of your mind whether or not
these propositions
jive with each other now we also make a
distinction between possible inferences
and necessary inferences
for if I say all men are mortal Socrates
is a man
therefore
Socrates is mortal
Descartes and all logicians would
realize that that conclusion
follows necessarily from the
relationship of the premises if all men
are mortal
and Socrates belongs to the class of men
then we know for sure
that Socrates is mortal
that is a necessary inference drawn from
the premises
though sometimes you can have possible
inferences which may or may not be true
but you don't want to confuse those with
necessary inferences and that's a
significant thing because many of the
conclusions that we reach today we reach
because we read something and we see
well on the basis of this information
it's possible that the conclusion would
be such and such and then we commit
ourselves resolutely to that conclusion
when if it's only a possible inference
it may not be true
to say that it's possibly true is one
thing to say that it's certainly true is
another
now I labor this point for this reason
Descartes was not satisfied with
reaching possible inferences he wanted
to construct a method of knowing
that was based first of all on the clear
and distinct ideas those necessary
truths
like the law of non-contradiction
and on
the necessary
inferences that could be made from those
primary truths let me read a statement
from his discourse on method
where he says this in the subjects we
propose to investigate
our inquiries should re should be
directed not to what others have thought
nor to what we ourselves conjecture
but to what we can clearly behold and
with certainty deduce
now that doesn't mean that he was saying
we ignore the wisdom of the ages or the
contributions of Scholars or of experts
today in the school system we insist
that our students when they're doing
research papers that they cite
authorities or cite sources of people
who have expertise in the various fields
that they're canvassing but the point
Descartes is making here is
even 50 000 Frenchmen can be wrong
it's one thing to be aware of what other
Scholars or other people have said on a
certain subject but the very fact that
they have said it
does not make it true
how many times have we seen in history
Generations after generations multitudes
of people carrying over Traditions that
finally are exposed as being wrong
so though you may be aware of what the
sum depository of of thinking is on a
given subject that in of itself doesn't
prove its truth
this is one of the things I loved so I
loved so much about Thomas Aquinas is
that when you're reading aquinas's
theology you rarely see him quoting
other theologians
he's reasoning it for you through and
through and the power of that hits you
between the eyes because you've got to
deal with his argument
there is an argument for everything that
he affirms and everything that he
asserts and this is what what Descartes
is getting at he said don't just tell me
what everybody else believes
give me the argument
show me its validity
and so he said even my own conjecture
does not bring certitude
but I want to cut through all of the
confusion of my day
and get down to those basic ideas those
basic truths that are indisputable
that I can take to the bank that I can
live my life on
on the basis of certitude
and so from this he set out on what I
call a systematic doubt process
by which
he being from Missouri that southern
part of France he he decided to question
any
thought or any proposition that he ever
heard to question it to death
he questioned whether the hand that he
saw in front of his face was really
there
he questioned his senses he said how do
I know
that what I am perceiving in the
external world really exists out there
or is not simply
a hallucination in my own mind or an
illusion perpetrated by some Wicked
devil who's fooling me
I can't I can't trust in the file
analysis with absolute certainty what I
perceive in the external world
I'm not going to trust
theological authorities I'm not going to
trust scientific authorities I'm going
to doubt everything that I can
conceivably doubt
so he embarked on this process where he
doubted everything
but the one thing he couldn't
doubt
was that he was doubting
because if you doubt
that you're doubting
what are you doing
you're doubting
he said so one thing I know for sure is
that I am doubting
because if I doubt that I'm doubting
I prove that I'm doubting
because to doubt doubt requires doubt
so he came to this certain conclusion
that he was doubting
then he said okay what else is clearly
contained within the idea of my doubting
well for something for someone to doubt
they must be thinking
because doubt is a form of thinking
you can't have doubt
without thought
because doubt is an element
of thought
okay so now he says if I'm doubting
then I know
that I'm thinking
now if I'm thinking what else does that
tell me through resistless logic
according to Descartes
well if I'm thinking
I'm having thought
there must be something that's doing the
thinking
because thought requires a thinker
and it's not your thought it's giving
rise to my doubts
it's my thought that I'm immediately
aware of through pure intuition to know
that I am the one who's thinking and I
am doubting and if I am thinking and I'm
doubting
I must be
so he gives us his famous formula that
we've all heard at one time or another
pronounced variously by different people
and I'm going to
give you this pronunciation
cogito
ergo
sum
now
perhaps the most important part of this
formula is the middle word
ergo
which means what
therefore
it's the word that signals a conclusion
a rational conclusion
and he's saying cogito I think I'm
cogitating
therefore
some
I am
so he finally reaches something about
which he can be
absolutely certain
namely his own existence and some people
look at that and laugh and they say what
a waste of Labor to go through all of
that only to come to a conclusion
that everybody already has at the
beginning
but it's very important to understand
rationalism that the starting point
for all rational
investigation now
is
self-consciousness
that's where it starts and according to
Descartes it's the only place it can
start
can't start with your Consciousness at
least it can't start with your
Consciousness for me it can't start with
God's Consciousness God can start with
God's Consciousness but I can't start
with God's Consciousness because
the only way I could have a
consciousness of God
would be for me to be having a
and so I have to First Trust that I am
being conscious before I can even think
about being conscious of God or anything
else
so that for Descartes the starting point
of all Philosophical
Investigation is with the self
doesn't mean that's where you end
but that's where you start with
self-consciousness
now we're going to look at our next
session about some of the implications
of this
and some questions that may be raised
about it and have been raised about it
but at least for now we understand why
in the midst of all this skepticism and
all this confusion Descartes sought
an undeniable absolutely certain
starting point for the Reconstruction of
knowledge